A Guide to the Papers of Lt. Colonel Howard Bertram Aison
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Papers of Lt. Colonel Howard Bertram Aison 1942-1963
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 61
4 linear feet; 8 document cases and 2 oversize boxes
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Gerald P. Gaidmore, June 1999
Biographical/Historical Information
Howard Bertram Aison was born in Chicago, Illinois on June 7, 1920. He served almost his entire life in the United States Army, serving in World War II, Korea, and Vietnam. He attended Georgetown University, graduating in 1942 with a Bachelor of Science in Foreign Service. He also participated in ROTC. On June 4, 1942, Aison was drafted into the United States Army. Although he had taken ROTC courses in college he chose to remain an enlisted man, feeling that he was not prepared to be an officer. He served in the 77th Ordnance Depot Company taking part in the Allied campaigns in North Africa, Italy, Southern France, and Germany.
After the war, Aison returned to civilian life, married, and began working as a salesman. He did not enjoy civilian life, however, and chose to reenlist in the Army, this time as an officer. He was commissioned a second Lieutenant in the Ordnance Department on August 6, 1948. On March 7, 1951, he was promoted to first Lieutenant in the Infantry and, a year later, was ordered to Korea. Aison was first assigned as a United Nations liaison officer with the 2nd Infantry Division, 8th Army. He was responsible for acting as the liaison between the U.S. Division and the United Nations' units serving with it. He then became a platoon leader in a weapons platoon, and then a rifle platoon. On July 6, 1952, he was awarded a Bronze star for actions during a patrol. He was transferred to Civil Assistance in the 2nd Division, where he took an active role in the formation of the "Friendship Home," an orphanage for Korean children. On July 31, 1953 he was promoted to Captain and returned home from Korea in September.
From March 1962 to March 1963, Aison served as senior advisor to the 6th Regiment, 2nd Infantry Division, I Corps, Army of the Republic of Vietnam. On October 21, 1963, he was awarded a Bronze star with first Oak Leaf cluster for "meritorious duty against hostile forces." He retired from the United States Army in 1969 as a Lieutenant Colonel. He resided in Virginia Beach where he worked in imports and exports and invested in real estate. In 1974, he separated from his wife, but never divorced. On August 28, 1997, Lt. Colonel Howard Bertram Aison (ret.) died in Virginia Beach.
Scope and Content Information
The Papers of Howard B. Aison, dating from 1942 to 1963, contains correspondence, photographs, military training manuals, orders, diaries, recollections, unit histories, commendations, printed material, artifacts, and maps. The bulk of the collection documents his service in the United States Army and his participation in World War II, Korea, and Vietnam. Also, includes papers accumulated during his years as a student at Georgetown University.
Organization
The collection is arranged into the following series: I. Correspondence; II. Military Records; III. Student Papers; IV. Printed Material; V. Maps; VI. Photographs; VII. Oversized materials; VIII. Artifacts.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence
  Contains letters, dated from August 1951 to September 1953, that Aison sent his wife. Documents his experiences training at Fort Leonard Wood, Missouri (August - December 1951) and Camp Gordon, Georgia (January 1952), and his service in Korea (March 1952 - September 1953). Discusses a variety of topics including training and drilling, army food, the weather, a soldier's social life, weaponry, military equipment and clothing, living quarters, the slowness of the mail, an assessment of the military situation in Korea in 1952, Korea's geography and climate, life at the front, the differences between what American soldiers collected as souvenirs to that of other United Nations' forces, French and British fighting forces, the bombing of enemy lines, bunker construction, interaction with soldiers from the Republic of Korea, supply problems, dealing with guerillas, the black market, Korean National Policemen, characteristics of the fighting in Korea, R & R in Japan, "The Friendship Home," Korean orphans, peace talks, South Korea's attitude toward the peace talks, demonstrations against peace talks, Sygman Rhee, troop entertainment by Mickey Rooney, Frances Langford, and Jon Hall, dealing with rodents and scavenging animals including a tiger, and Chinese propaganda. Several letters deserve special note. A letter dated April 2, 1952 includes surrender leaflets fired into enemy lines. A letter dated July 6, 1952 recounts the patrol for which he was awarded a bronze star including citation, map of patrol, and interrogation of prisoners. A letter dated March 22, 1953 discusses the exploits of Courtney Mansfield, an African- American soldier.
  - Fort Leonard Wood August-December 1951, 4 folders (Box-folder Box 1, Folders 1-4)
  - Chinese People's Volunteers Christmas Card 1951 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Camp Gordon, Georgia January, 1952, 2 folders (Box-folder Box 1, Folders 6, 7)
  - Korea March 1952-September 1953, 18 folders (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8 - Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series II: Military Records
  This series is divided into four subseries: A. World War II; B. Korea; C. Vietnam; D. Training.
  - Sub-Series A: World War II
    Includes an induction notice, promotion certificates, orders, customs declarations for war trophies, a diary, and recollections. The diary records his service during the war for the year 1945. The recollections detail Aison's service in Anzio, Italy and Southern France. Other material of note are instructions for the treatment of the enemy, instructions for the conduct of U.S. troops in North Africa, and a history of the 77th Ordnance Depot Company.
    - Timeline and Notes of Service 1942-1945 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Draft Induction; Promotion Certificate; FDR Form Letter (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Orders Feb. 1943-Feb, 1944 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Diary 1945 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Recollections - Anzio (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Recollections - Italy (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Recollections - Southern France (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 15)
    - History of the 77th Ordnance Depot Company (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Home Address of the 77th Ordnance Depot Company (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Certificates, Affidavits, and Custom Declarations - War Trophies (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Vital Information on Conduct of U.S. Troops; Instructions for Treatment of Enemy (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Sub-Series B: Korea
    Includes orders, training bulletins, commendations, recommendations for bravery and promotions, and standard operating procedures for Civil Affairs. Of note are the training bulletins relating to patrol actions, the combat leaders guide, and general orders for sentinels, and an ID card and pass issued to Korean civilians.
    - Orders 1951-1953 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Recommendations and Commendations for Heroism, Promotion, and Superior Service (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Financial Documents (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 22)
    - 2nd Infantry Division Civil Affairs, 2 folders (Box-folder Box 2, Folders 23, 24)
    - Staff Director - 2nd Infantry Division September 1, 1953 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 25)
    - The Friendship House (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Security Codes (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Training Bulletin; Patrol Plan 1952 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 28)
    - General Orders for Sentinels; Combat Leaders Guide (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Employee ID Card and Pass (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Sub-Series C: Vietnam
    Includes orders issued in 1962, and a certificate for the Bronze Star.
    - Award of Bronze Star Medal (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Orders November 21, 1962 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Sub-Series D: Training
    Includes training material collected from various training schools such as: The U.S. Army Infantry School at Fort Benning, Georgia, and Manpower Control Officers Course at Fort Benjamin Harrison, Indiana. Noteworthy is the syllabi, course descriptions, and training manuals from the U.S. Army Special Warfare School.
    - U.S. Army Infantry School - Ft. Benning, Georgia (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Manpower Control Officers Course 1961, 10 folders (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 34 - Box 3, Folder 7)
    - U.S. Army Special Warfare School - Syllabi 1964 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 8)
    - U.S. Army Special Warefare School - Counterinsurgency Operations Officers Course 1964 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "Pre-requisites for Resistance Movements and Guerrilla Operations" Counter Insurgency Dept., U.S. Army Special Warefare School (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 10)
    - "Communist Ideology Strategy and Tactics" Counter Insurgengy Dept., U.S. Army Special Warfare School (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "Readings in Guerrilla Warfare" U.S. Army Special Warfare School (Fort Bragg) (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "Readings in Psychological Operations" Table of Contents (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 13)
    - "Readings in Psychological Warfare", 8 folders (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 14-21)
    - Certificates of Completion (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Sub-Series E: General Records
    Contains promotions, 1948-1961.
    - Promotions 1948-1961 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series III: Student Papers
  Includes essays and notes relating to courses in international law, and exporting. Of interest are notes pertaining to hypnotism, and a list of the Dewey Decimal System.
  - Georgetown University - School of Foreign Service - International Law (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 3)
  - School of Foreign Service - Georgetown University - Exporting I-304 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Government Export Policies (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Essays, 2 folders (Box-folder Box 4, Folders 6, 7)
  - Georgetown University - School of Foreign Service - Staple Commodities of World Trade, 2 folders (Box-folder Box 4, Folders 8, 9)
  - Notes on Hypnotism (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Dewey Decimal System (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Printed Material
  Includes issues from Democracy Versus Communism Series, and the Foreign Service Log, military unit histories and yearbooks, cartoons from Bill Mauldin and Dick Wingert, an article on the "Friendship Home" published in the Pittsburgh Press, a Life issue dated January 25, 1963, a Pacific Stars and Stripes regarding the Korean War, and an issue of the Times of Viet Nam regarding the Battle of Phuoc Chau. Of note is a collection of phrase books, language guides, and pocket guides of Germany, France, Italy, Japan, Korea, North Africa, and Russia.
  - Democracy Faces Communism Series No. 1-10 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Foreign Service Log, Vol. III, No. 1-3, 5-14 October 1940 - May 1941 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Foreign Service Log, Vol. IV, No. 1, 4-6, 8 October 1941 - April 1942 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 14)
  - "Second to None" A Short History of Second Infantry Division, 1918-1952 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Blood and Fire" Victory in Europe 63rd Infantry Division (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "Don't Be a Sucker in Germany" Special Orders for German-American Relations Deutsche Flugzeuge (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "A Pocket Guide to Italy;" "Soldier's Guide to Italy" (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "Russian Language Guide" (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "The Airborne" - Classbook Airborne Class 12 June 29, 1956 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 6)
- Series V: Maps and Overlays
  Contains maps and overlays of regions and countries throughout the world. Appear to be used for military strategic studies purposes for Division Operations, U.S. Army Command and General Staff College (Ft. Leavenworth)
  - Alaska (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Austria (Amstetten - Wieselburg) (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Austria and Italy (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Europe (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Germany (Erfurt - Weissenfels) (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Germany (Essen - Bochum) (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Germany (Hof - Plauen) (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Japan (Chitese - Iwanizawa) (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Poland and Germany (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Puerto Rico (Ponce) (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 1)
  - South Africa (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Southwestern Asia (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Southwest Asia (Damascus - Moussa Ler) (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 4)
  - United States (Oklahoma City - Wichita Falls) (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Western United States (Kansas) (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Maps and Overlays (No geographic distinction) (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Item Inventory (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 8)
- Series VI: Photographs
  Documents Aison's service in the military, primarily during World War II and Vietnam. Many of the photographs from World War II are labeled. Of note are two scrapbooks containing photographs of his service in Vietnam. Also of interest are postcards of Paris and Constantine, Algeria, and five panorama photos. Two of these panoramas are from his father's service in the military: Camp Grant, Officers 161st Depot Brigade, November 20, 1917; and Provisional Medical Regiment, U.S. Army Fort Snelling, Minnesota, July 1924. The others are: Georgetown University, 143rd Annual Commencement, May 25, 1942; 77th Ordnance Depot Co., "1st Anniversary Overseas," Caserto, Italy, November 1943; Assoc. Inf. Co. Officers Course No. 2, 24th Co., 1st Stu. Regt., March 26, 1954 - November 18, 1954, Fort Benning, Georgia.
  - World War II, 4 folders (Box-folder Box 8, Folders 1-4)
  - Vietnam, 2 folders (Box-folder Box 8, Folders 5, 6)
  - Military (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Holiday Greetings (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Postcards - Constantine, Algeria (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Prints - Paris (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Prints - Miscellaneous (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Negatives (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbooks - Vietnam, Oversize Box (Box Box 9)
  - Panorama Photographs, Oversize Box (Box Box 9)
- Series VII: Oversized Materials
  Includes promotional posters for bullfighting events in Spain dated 1919, 1947, and 1958, a color sketch of a young boy, certificates and diplomas for military training, certificates and diplomas from Bryn Mawr School and Hirsch High School in Chicago, and Georgetown University, and a certificate of confirmation dated 1935.
  - Certificates, Diplomas, Posters, Oversize Box (Box Box 9)